[訪問佐爾丹．丹尼斯]
So here we are with Zoltan Dienes,
the author of this book,
今天我們訪問佐爾丹．丹尼斯(Zoltan Dienes)
他是「Understanding Psychology as a Science」的作者
Understanding Psychology as a Science.
今天我們訪問佐爾丹．丹尼斯(Zoltan Dienes)
他是「Understanding Psychology as a Science」的作者
Zoltan, it's really nice
that you want to be here.
佐爾丹你好，謝謝你接受訪問
Nice to be here.
這是我的榮幸
Take some time from this
conference that we're at.
我們在這場研討會的空檔做個訪談
Taking some time for this interview.
So first of all I was wondering,
how did you get into this topic?
首先我想問的是
你是如何開始接觸這本書的主題?
What decided that you would write about
things like this or find them interesting?
是有什麼發現讓你感到特別有興趣的嗎?
My interest goes back quite a way,
actually.
其實我從很小就對這方面主題有興趣了
My mother was a Scientologist.
我母親是位科學教(山達基)的信徒
And the headmaster of the sixth form
I was in gave me a book on Popper.
我高中時的校長送了我一本卡爾．波普(Karl Popper)的書
So I read about Karl Popper and
波普的書討論許多關於科學真偽的議題
he discusses what makes something
a science or not a science.
波普的書討論許多關於科學真偽的議題
And that had a pretty big impact on me and
how I
他的書深深影響了當時的我
viewed various movements and what they
might call themselves a science or not.
如何看待周遭事物是否為真科學
The fact that also it's not just a label,
but Popper wanted to point out that
波普想指出的重點不在於分別科學的「真」或「假」
how you approach that really matters to
the quality of the knowledge that you get.
而是你如何正確地理解你吸收的知識
I see that you have some interests
in one of the examples comes from
我注意到你書中有些例子來自
precognition research and psi research.
超感知覺及超能力的研究
And you did some studies
about it yourself, right?
你對這方面有所涉獵，是吧?
Yes, now there's a topic
where the philosophy of science,
是的，這是現在的科學哲學
the philosophy of
statistics really comes up.
也是統計哲學正在熱烈探討的一個問題
So if you investigate
a topic where a lot of people
如果今天你想研究的假設
think the hypothesis theory has
a very low or high probability.
被絕大多數人認為是真的機率很高或很低
Then just using p-values and p less
than 0.05, somehow doesn't seem right.
那麼只看p值及設定顯著水準(0.05)似乎是不夠的
And then to make a binding decision at
the end of that doesn't seem right.
以此推論出來的結果也不像是對的
Whereas saying there's a certain
amount of evidence here and
實際情況比較像是今天若有一定量的事實證據
that will change your
opinion by a certain amount.
這些證據累積一定程度能夠改變你對某件事的想法
Just seeing the better way
of dealing with theories
我只是覺得該有更好的方式來看待這些理論
where people might have radically
views about them in the first place.
尤其是在那些人們通常有著先驗信念的情況下
So that was in fact my first
application of Bayesian statistics.
這也是為何我的書會從貝氏統計開始討論起
All right, so
mainly you were doing that research,
所以這就是為何你的研究
that's when you ventured into this
direction of Bayesian statistics.
會從貝氏統計開始"挑戰"
Yeah, initially,
1980s I was doing my PhD at Oxford and
是的，我和貝氏統計相遇
是1980年代我還在牛津大學讀博士時
Oxford invited this statistician from UCL,
John Kier,
學校請了一位倫敦大學(UCL)的統計學家John Kier來授課
who had been Piaget's statistician and
Hans Eysenck's statistician.
他曾與心理學大師皮亞傑(Piaget)及
漢斯·艾森克(Hans Eysenck)合作
And he came to teach
the PhD students at Oxford,
牛津大學請他每周三下午來教博士生統計
every Wednesday afternoon, statistics.
I found him quite captivating,
charismatic.
他是個相當有魅力的統計學家
But he would teach just
whatever he wanted to teach.
不過他只教他想教的東西
And one term he said I'm
going to teach you Bayes.
其中有個學期他說我們來上貝式統計吧
And by the end of the term, there's just
me and one other person sitting there.
到了學期末教室內只剩下我跟另一個學生
[LAUGH]
And I found it absolutely fascinating,
那時我發現了貝式統計的迷人之處
but the other people just thought this is
not relevant to my thesis, I'll disappear.
但大多數同學只覺得與他們的論文無關
就翹課了
All right.
好的
So
my little Bayesian base factor calculator
所以我開發的貝式統計計算程式
(見Zoltan Dienes個人網站)
actually programmed at that point.
從那個時候就開始開發了
(見Zoltan Dienes個人網站)
Okay.
的確
Way back then.
那個年代
Like 1980s.
1980年代
So that's actually
an interesting point, right?
這真是件有趣的事
So you say that most of
these students slowly left.
所以你說當時那堂課的同學後面都逐漸離開教室
But now, of course,
if you write this book, there's a lot of
但現在你寫的這本書
topics in here that has to do with
Bayesian statistics and likelihood.
裏頭有許多關於貝式統計及似然性的討論
So apparently you thought
it was worthwhile that
這麼說你認為當初堅持到最後
the students shouldn't leave.
是有價值的囉?
Actually you thought it was worthwhile
to explain more to students about this.
事實上你應該認為這些知識是值得學生們更深入的了解吧
So why do you think it's important that
students learn about these things?
那麼你認為為什麼學生該要學習這些知識呢?
It's important because there's a debate
about how one should do statistics
我想這些知識很重要
是因為一直以來有相當多關於統計推論的辯論
that isn't settled, or
it seemed to be settled but it wasn't.
表面上大家好像有共識了
實則不然
And the way we had settled on
doing things caused problems,
而大家曾以為是對的的「共識」已經造成許多問題
that is why we had the credibility crisis,
that was a big part of it.
這也是為何最近學界開始對過去心理學研究結果產生質疑
And now people are really thinking
about how should we do statistics,
也因此現在大家開始認真思考，
究竟該怎麼使用統計學
how should we do science and
I think in ten years' time
去做科學研究
我想在十年後
results sections are going to look
rather different than they do now.
我們使用統計的方式將會跟現在大不相同
And you can either be ahead
of the curve on that or
你可以選擇現在就開始改變
you can be desperately
trying to catch up later.
或是日後才努力追趕前人改變的腳步
And the people we need to reach
are the current students coming up.
而這個時代正在學習的學生們
They need to understand these issues,
and where researchers have gone wrong in
他們必須了解問題所在
以及前人所犯過的錯誤
the past that led to science that
wasn't really that credible in the end.
那些造成當代科學不能被全然信任的錯誤
And if you don't understand statistics,
and the philosophy of
如果你不徹底了解統計學
及科學哲學的話
science more generally,
then you'll make the same mistakes again.
你將會犯下同樣的錯誤
So, I think this is the time to change.
所以我認為是時候做出改變了
Change is happening.
事實上改變已在發生
Ten years' time sounds not very different.
或許十年能做的的改變有限
I actually think in a hundred years time,
people will look back on how
但我認為一百年後
當人們回首過去百年的進展
we do science now and it will be a bit
like how we look back hundred years ago.
正如同我們現在回顧一百年前的科學
It's like really, they did it like that?
我們會想「以前真的這麼做嗎?」
「這樣做也太粗糙了」
That's pretty primitive.
我們會想「以前真的這麼做嗎?」
「這樣做也太粗糙了」
Yeah.
的確
And a lot of the changes
that will be coming about and
另外也會一直有新的改變出現
affecting how we do science in the future,
they're happening right now.
影響我們做科學的方式
All right.
So that's quite exciting, in a way.
聽起來真讓人興奮
Yeah, yeah I agree.
沒錯，我也這麼覺得
Okay, very good.
好的
So when you were you exhibiting
all these things for
所以你培養這些統計分析與推論的技術
yourself, these statistical techniques and
figuring out, mainly this was because you
needed to analyze your own data, right?
是為了分析你的研究數據資料，是嗎?
I mean, you're not In principle
statistician yourself.
我意思是說
儘管你本身並非統計學家出身
No trained as a psychologist, exactly.
的確，我並不是心理學家出身
So you're trying to figure out how to
use this, so what things were most helpful
那麼在你學習使用這些技術的過程中
to you or most insightful or eye opening
when you were learning about these things?
有哪些方法是你覺得特別有用
或是特別令你大開眼界的經驗?
I think when I wrote the book and
I don't know if it comes across there but
我想當初我在寫書的時候
probably as leaning towards
a likelihood approach.
儘管並非特意
卻不自覺多少偏重似然性取向
That sort of of.
儘管並非特意
卻不自覺多少偏重在似然性取向
>> It comes across
a little bit [INAUDIBLE].
的確是有點
Yeah.
I noticed a little bit.
我有注意到
Yes and either that obeys for
對我來說特別重要的是
me a big issue was how you deal
with non-significant results.
如何解讀非顯著的統計分析結果
because in my field, non-significant
results were often used [INAUDIBLE].
因為在我的領域中
常使用非顯著結果做統計推論
My field being unconscious knowledge,
unconscious perception, and
我的研究主題是無意識的(知識)與知覺
perceived learning and how you establish
perception is unconscious, subliminal.
以及在無意識或潛意識下的學習與感知
Or learning is implicit is often by
getting a non-significant result.
還有隱性學習的研究經常出現非顯著的統計結果
And but just getting
a non-significant result in itself
如果只是報告這些非顯著的結果
does not have evidential value,
so what do you do?
證據就沒有有足夠說服力
那麼該怎麼辦呢?
So I was looking looking at light and
bayes.
所以我轉向運用貝式統計
And then just through having to
really apply them in real situations.
我試著應用貝式統計在實際的研究中
Not is about statistics but
do psychology and apply those techniques.
不只是應用其統計方式
還運用這些技術在心理學研究過程
I found bayes was just most useful.
我發現貝式統計是最實用的
Because typically when you have a theory,
you're saying,
特別是當你有一個理論時
well there's a range of possibilities for
what the population hypothesis could be,
假設成立的機率會落在一個可能的區間範圍
some are more plausible than others.
某些機率值可能較其他值更合理些
And as soon as you accept that and
一旦你有這樣的想法
want to get evidence from the hypothesis
you'll have to base factors.
下一步就是找出足夠的證明支持假設
進而得到理論的基礎因子
And I've just found that
enormously helpful.
而我發現貝式定理在這個情況下特別有用
If you look at how I write papers now
even compared to three years ago,
拿我現在寫的研究報告與三年前相比
it's just radically different.
你會發現它們相當的不同
I look back to how I read papers,
really just bear in mind,
而我重新回首讀過的研究報告
just following through the logic
that's contained in that book, but
只是這次完全跟隨著我書中所闡述的邏輯
just following it through and actually
applying it every step of the way.
一步一步地用貝氏統計方法閱讀報告
It's turned around how I do science.
書中闡述的我如何改變做科學的方式
So you'd say you're still
learning about this book.
所以你意思是說
你至今仍在持續學習
Looked into yourself.
並省思自己做科學的方式
Still learning, exactly.
是的，持續學習
So since 2008,
when the book was published,
自從這本書在2008年出版之後
I've been thinking about how to
actually apply it in real situations.
我便一直在思考能夠實際應用的例子
So exactly the same logic that's in there,
一個能夠應用書中介紹的邏輯方法
but putting it into practice
is what I've been working on.
將其應用在實際研究上的例子
All right, great.
好的
Thanks so much.
謝謝你
[訪問結束]